do
[Music]
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to a new episode of the ask
a budget show today we discuss
science and technology and all that good
wonderful stuff
so before we get into it as always let
me see who all is there with us i can
see abbay
shreya crazy brain arnob
akwan bhavesh nishtoi durga
rama ranga brio raj
and a whole lot of other
other people good evening good day all
of you thank you for being here on this
live show
so
today we discuss
science technology and all that
wonderful stuff so let's see what all
questions we have
for today let's begin
with question one what is question one
uncle says
why do all the space station centers
why are all the space station centers
situated on the east coast of india and
why not the west coast
that is interesting good question
interesting question so uh when we talk
about the various it's not space center
stations these are the space launch
the locations from which rockets are
launched and they are typically on the
east coast of india let's take a look at
the map
we should we shall begin today with the
map so here is the map let's see the
east coast of india
so uh we have something called wheeler
island or or nowadays it's called kalam
island apj abdul kalam island or
something
it's uh
off the coast of orissa somewhere over
here i'm not sure what exactly it is
uh let us see
kalam island
where is that yeah it's here
abdul kalam island so it's an island
near
off the east coast of india this is from
where from where you typically launch
various
rockets and i i'm sure there is one or
two more of these rocket launch stations
so this is what the place looks like and
isro has a facility over here there will
be
a place from which rockets are launched
and
typically all of these places from where
we launch rockets are on the east coast
of india
yes
and even when it comes to the us
the united states
uh cape canaveral cape canada etc it's
on the east coast of the us
the florida coast
even the french they have their
place called kuhu
which is in french guyana cool over here
yes this little place
uh they launched their rockets from here
the aryan rockets it's on the east coast
of the uh
of the continent of south america and so
on so the question is why is this so why
is it always the east coast why not the
west coast right
so
uh first of all let's understand what an
orbit is
you launch a rocket
to place things into earth orbit the
earth is round
and you place things into orbit so what
is earth orbit it's when a satellite or
a spacecraft or or space station or
whatever
is placed
in a trajectory that goes around the
earth at approximately the same height
above the surface
of the earth
so this is essentially falling so fast
that you don't hit the earth you're
falling in a forward direction
you're falling forward not down so you
keep for and there is a certain thing
called an orbital velocity depending on
the distance from the surface you have a
certain orbital velocity so
so what you do
is you place a satellite or or an object
in earth orbit at a certain height
and you want it to go around the earth
at a certain velocity so that it doesn't
fall down it just keeps on flying
so what you do
now we know that the earth rotates right
we have day and night because of the
rotation of the earth
now in what direction does the earth
rotate that is the question the earth
rotates
from east to west
and how do we know this well
where does the sun rise in the morning
does it rise in the west or does it rise
in the east
the sun rises in the east
and therefore the earth is rotating
towards the east
from in that direction
so that rotational motion of the earth
if you can use that in rocket launches
it will
it will give you an extra kick or an
extra amount of momentum to the rocket
and if you
make the orbit of the spacecraft in the
same direction as the rotational earth
that has an advantage right
so that's the reason why typically to
make use of the additional boost that
the earth's rotation gives you you
typically launch your rockets as close
to the equator as possible and you
launch them
in the eastward direction now if you
have a
rocket launch station on the west coast
for instance
and let's say you launch a rocket in the
rocket fails and it crashes down to the
ground
and you're gonna launch it towards the
east direction
it's gonna end up crashing
onto the
mainland on perhaps inhabited territory
right so you don't want that to happen
you want the rocket if it fails to crash
into the ocean
and therefore we launch rockets from the
east coast so in case something we're
gonna we're gonna first of all launch
them in the eastward direction yes it
will go up and then it will go east and
then if the rocket fails for whatever
reason it will crash into the ocean and
not on
some inhabited place a town a city a
village or whatever right so that is the
reason why the space launch stations of
india and most other places are launched
are located on the east coast
so that if something goes wrong the
rocket can be safely crashed into the
ocean and not on
land that's the simple reason
all right
let's go to the next question
koshi says
recently the james webb claims that big
bang never happened what do you think
about it okay
the james webb space telescope makes
observations it doesn't make claims
and the people working with this
on the space on this telescope etc they
simply
uh handle it
they uh they ensure that it is pointed
in the right direction from time to time
i mean it has time slots available for
various observations so they ensure they
do all the administration they do all
the pointing of the telescope in those
directions they do the maintenance work
you know making sure that everything
everything's working and so on so the
james webb space telescope people the
crew the people who are working the
scientists and engineers who are working
on this project don't make any claims
they simply operate the telescope and
ensure it keeps running properly and not
a single second of time is wasted right
because time is precious
now the james webb spirit the space
telescope as we know has brought out has
given us lots of new images in the very
short period of time it's been working
and it's already
transforming the way we understand the
universe
now based on some of these images some
people
some scientists
some journalists etc have made some
outlandish claims like the big bang
never happened it's it's uh
bringing the big bang theory into
question and so on and so forth yeah
that's what is happening some people are
making such claims uh you see that on
the media that the big bang may have
never happened the big bang theory may
be wrong and james webb is upending
science and astronomy and astrophysics
and all that
all nonsense
so what's happened
it's the telescope has given us images
of the oldest galaxies that are known to
have existed right i mean the oldest
galaxies ever ever captured on
photographic images that's what we are
seeing
the earliest galaxy that had ever been
captured
in a photograph
was by the james was by the hubble space
telescope which was launched in the
1990s i think
i think 1990s or 1980s whatever it's an
old telescope it's still operational so
the oldest galaxy that it had
photographed well it dated back to about
about 410 million years after the big
bang
so that's the earliest known galaxy
the
before the james webb telescope became
operational and the oldest galaxies that
the hubble telescope photographed
where rather primitive galaxies they
were
they were like blobs
they were not disc shaped and all that
right
so
point number one the earliest galaxy
thus far before the jwst was
dates back to about 410
million years after the big bang and
secondly the oldest galaxies that the
hubble photographed were not well formed
galaxies they look like very primitive
and diffuse galaxies like blobs yeah
now the jwst has given us images of much
older galaxies the oldest galaxies that
the jwst has been able to photograph
date back to around i think 250 or so
million years after the big bang close
to 200 million years after the big bang
that's a giant leap forward so we are
seeing galaxies that are really really
old around 200 to 250 million years
after the big bang and secondly
many of these galaxies that the jwst has
photographed are spiral shaped they are
not
blobs
they are well defined
which means that they have been in by
the
even 200 million years ago or whenever
whatever date it dates back to the
galaxy was already well formed multiple
galaxies which means they had been in
existence for a longer time than than
the time period that we know of 2 8 20
or 250 million years after the big bang
so that tells us that the earliest stage
of galaxy formation was earlier than
what we thought or imagined or or
believed
until now it was believed that the
earliest galaxies formed around 400
million years after big bang and those
must have been primitive galaxies and
they would have taken time to take well
defined shapes like spiral shapes etc
and now we are finding something very
different the earliest known galaxies
date back to around 200 or so million
years after the big bang and they are
already well defined they have got
spiral shapes so that is like a big
discovery for sure
now does it prove the big bang never
happened what nonsense
what absolute utter nonsense
it doesn't say anything like that
the best evidence that we have
from all the data we have collected over
the past hundred or so years
astrophysical data astronomically
etcetera
the the um the evidence that we have
from the uh
cosmic microwave background notation all
of this stuff all the theoretical
evidence all of it indicates that a big
bang what we call the so-called big bank
did indeed happen if we extrapolate back
in time we find that the universe would
have started as a big
as a infinitely infinite decimal small
infinitely dense infinitely hot point
of of energy right everything would have
been concentrated into that that is
about 13.8 billion years before today
i've explained many times why we why
that's the best theory that we have and
by all the observational and other
experimental and theoretical evidence
indicates this actually happened yeah
now
the new discovery of these oldest
galaxies dates back to about 200 or so
million years after the big bang how can
it indicate the big bang never happened
it simply tells us that yeah our
understanding of physics may not be
entirely correct
that galaxy formation seems to have
happened
significantly
before what we thought it would at what
time it would happen so maybe there is
something new
in physics in the initial conditions
after the big bang etc that we are not
aware of or that we have not considered
or something like that
it doesn't mean that big bang nearly
never happened right
so uh and the earliest
all the observational evidence does
indicate that there was a big bang kind
of thing the cosmic microwave background
today it's still there
it indicates it is it is the signature
after glow of the first light after the
big bang right and so on so all these
claims that people are making various
people are making even scientists are
making some some scientists are even
making the claim that there is something
uh
that that maybe the big bang did not
happen or maybe the james webb
discoveries and images and observations
uh throw doubt upon the big bang theory
no it is not so
they certainly will make us think
in different directions yeah
and we will need to uh understand and
answer certain questions
as to why we have well-formed
well-defined galaxies so early in the
history of the universe yeah so that
these questions will have to be taken up
and addressed satisfactorily answered
satisfactorily maybe we may uh
maybe it has something to do with the
nature of with the nature of dark matter
or dark energy because much and about
black holes
did primordial black holes form very
early and
did they end up being the seeds of
supermassive black holes around which
galaxies formed when would this have
happened what does dark matter and dark
energy have to do with this what is the
i mean dark matter and dark energy are
kind of dynamic in nature you know the
compositions and percentages over over
the uh periods of the of the universe's
history have changed yes so all of this
is exciting
what these new observational uh ever
this new observational evidence is very
exciting every time you find something
that
that makes you question what you thought
thus far it's always exciting because it
tells you how much more you have you
still have to discover in physics so
clearly
there are some new uh
there is a lot of new evidence here
which may make us which may throw some
interesting light on dark matter dark
energy the early universe the way the
universe evolved and all that but it
does not call into question the big bang
that is still the best theory that we
have and none of this puts even one
percent of of uh a doubt on the overall
theory
in the overall uh
history that we know of the universe the
big the so-called big bang cosmology
yeah
so yeah
it's it's not true at all some people
have made this interpretation that the
it calls into question the big bang
theory which is completely incorrect
okay video says uh how do scientists
know if an animal is extinct do they
look everywhere physically and couldn't
find that animal
the fantastic giant tortoise which was
believed to have gone extinct had been
has been found alive recently yeah okay
um
how do you know an animal is extinct
well there are various criteria that
have changed over time i think at one
point in time in the 20th century the
criterion was that the
if an animal or a species has not been
observed
for 50 years then you can declare it
extinct that was one criterion i'm not
sure if it is still around that
criterion uh so what are the criteria
that we use to to
say that an animal has gone extinct
first of all there should be no more
observational evidence of the animal
let's say you're talking about a fish
now some animals you can easily say that
they're extinct some animals are very
it's it's very hard to say if they're
extremely not for instance land animals
are visible on land so it's easier
to say if they're extinct or not
compared to fish
because fish you have to go deeper i
mean under the ocean under the seas to
find them and some fish
live kilometers under the ocean
the giant overfish is a massive massive
fish but it lea it lives i believe
several kilometers
at a depth of more than one kilometer
under the ocean now who's gonna go down
there and see it
so it's harder to tell whether such
species are extinct or not compared to
uh species of animals that live on land
if you have a large animal
then it's easier to observe it let's say
you have the cheetah the indian cheetah
we know it's extinct the last time it
was observed was more than 100 it was
around 100 or so years ago maybe 90
years ago
in in a densely populated region like
the indian subcontinent
if for the last 90 years nobody has seen
an indian cheetah it means that animal
is extinct the cheetah is still
known to exist in iran
west of india but in india it is extinct
so
that's one one way of doing it secondly
you see whether the habitat of the
animal exists or not let's say a certain
species of bird can only thrive in a
forest that has a certain kind of tree
and now we know those forests are no
longer there we have eaten them up we
have deforested the land and those trees
no longer exist that can support the
existence of this bird species and if we
know for sure that these forests are
gone then we can safe
with with a great amount of certitude
with a large amount of certitude that
that bird also would have gone extinct
especially if there is no more
observational photographic or anecdotal
visible evidence that the bird has been
uh seen in recent times that's one
that's another way of doing it
so you don't
look everywhere physically you cannot go
and map every single point and and
coordinate of the planet it's not
possible but there are these rough
criteria that we employ and it's they
are not
foolproof
you know
for instance have you heard of the silo
kant
let me put the c locant on the screen
c-o-e-l-a-c-a-n-t-h i believe that is
the spelling oh my goodness i got the
spelling right
that is fantastic
okay let's see the silo celocanth
so the selochanth is a species of fish
it was believed to have gone extinct 66
million years ago with the dinosaurs
so this
fish species was believed to be extinct
for 66 million years for 66 million
years we only knew about this fish from
the fossil record a massive fish and
then it was rediscovered it still exists
it exists
in the indian ocean of the coast of
africa of the coast of indonesia also i
believe and so on
and it was discovered in a fisherman's
market where it was being sold
yeah so it's it's it's like a stone it's
like a dinosaur era fish but it still
exists
it's it's still caught by some fishermen
and sold
in in fisherman's markets right so this
is an example of a fish that had not and
and the thing is it lives deep under the
oceans it's not a surface fish it's not
the fish that you will see on the
surface it will be caught only once in a
while when when people go really deep
with their fish hooks and whatever right
so it was believed to be extinct and
then it was rediscovered so so that's an
example so this uh declaring a species
extinct is never foolproof
uh
you may have species declared extinct
that may reappear for instance there is
this uh creature called uh the thylacine
right
this scene t-t-h-y-l-a-c-i-n-e
which is a tasmanian tiger where is it
let's put it on the screen
so they have you have this beast called
the tasmanian tiger i think it went
extinct over about a century or so ago
it's not been seen but you keep getting
anecdotal evidence from time to time
of people seeing this beast
it's it's a marsupial it's uh it used to
exist in australia
and
the
it was in zoos and all but it was hunted
down by i don't know by by humans or by
dogs i'm not sure but it seems to have
gone extinct and yet from time to time
you have people reporting a sighting of
this animal and even in new zealand i
believe people have reported sightings
of this animal in in recent in
reasonably recent times yeah
so it may so be that it's not exactly
extinct but the population is very low
and maybe they are very shy and they
stay out of
out of
range of humans possibly yeah
and then of course you have animals like
the mythical
uh yeti the migoi
of the himalayan region i mean locals in
bhutan and sikkim in northern india
in tibet etc they speak about this
animal as if it exists we've never
actually seen one or captured one but
yeah you know there is enough total
evidence that something is maybe around
even the indian army had put out a tweet
with the
photographs of some mysterious
footprints that are clearly not human in
the snow yeah
in in northern india in the himalayan
region so it's possible that there are
species that exist that we don't know of
that we have never really
obtained hard evidence of it's also
possible that some species of animal
that have been declared extinct may
still exist so it is not
a process it is not something that you
can say for certain ever and certainly
you cannot look everywhere physically to
go and look for
for such extinct species so it's a
statistical thing you know probably
if the probability is very high that the
animal is extinct you go over and
declare it extinct and if it reappears
well you change
you change that
yeah the classification or
categorization
okay
next question vishal says will the comet
smith um
swift tuttle swift tuttle will the comet
swift turtle which is heading on a
collision course with the earth on 17th
august 216
end most forms of life on earth and is
it true that the collision will be way
more powerful than the explosion of a
million nuclear bombs put together
okay this comet swift tuttle
it appeared if i'm not mistaken in 1992
1992 i believe and i'm not sure if it
was visible to the naked eye but it was
clearly visible on telescopes and
possibly even binoculars so this
comet appeared last in 1992 i think it
is a period of 130 130 three years or so
and if you do the math it
it will appear in 21 26 i believe not 20
21 26 if i'm not mistaken so this may
not be in this this this here date may
not be entirely correct it's probably
2126 yeah and uh so people obviously
take these things very seriously
especially astronomers and all so they
it's possible to calculate the exact
date when a comet will be at the closest
approach to earth right because of
orbital dynamics dynamics we can do the
calculations based on what we know
based on past data observational data so
it was first calculated that uh there
could be an impact with earth on
14th of august
2026.
then more observational data was was
looked at the calculation was refined
and it looks like it will not exactly
collide with with our planet but it will
come quite close it will come to about
70 times the earth moon distance
so the earth moon distance is 385 kilo
384 000 kilometers that's the distance
from the earth to the moon 384 000
kilometers
so multiply that by approximately 70 you
will get the distance
the closest approach of this comet to
the earth
in 2026 in august 26. i'm not sure what
exactly the date is the hypothesized
date of the impact was 14th august i'm
not sure what the new calculations say
but it's certainly in august 2026.
so most likely it's not going to collide
but it's certainly a comment that needs
to be looked at very carefully because
it's a near-earth comet i mean it's a
comet that tends to keep coming close to
the earth moon system which is always
something you should take very seriously
yeah
uh
now uh
let's say hypothetically this goddamn
rock
impacts the earth what's it gonna be
like so first of all it's uh
it's it's it's a large
comet it's it's uh
the
the comet or asteroid or object that
collided with our planet 66 million
years ago the so-called chicholu
impactor which wiped out the non-avian
dinosaurs
that asteroid comet rock whatever you
call it is believed to have had a
diameter of about 10 kilometers
10 kilometers imagine a ball a football
with with a diameter of 10 kilometers
approximately that's what it was like
right
now this comet swift turtle
i think it has a nucleus
with a diameter of 26 kilometers that's
two and a half times more than two and a
half times
the diameter of the chipshot impactor
which
which was a disastrous cataclysm for us
for for for our dinosaur friends not for
us we survived our ancestors survived so
this swift tuttle nucleus is 26
kilometers in diameter roughly
now if you imagine that this thing
impacts the earth at roughly 60
kilometers per second
which is believed to be approximately
the speed of the chichalub impact
so if swift turtle hits the earth at
approximately 60 kilometers per second
not hour second 60 kilometers per second
is going to release about 30 times
the energy of the chips loop impactor
now i don't remember how much energy the
impact released but it was millions of
times the energy of the hiroshima
nuclear test
yeah
so that's how it was so yeah if it
happens it's going to be a
massive
massive cataclysm on a scale that's
unimaginable to us
it's gonna cause a mass extinction for
sure it's going to cause tsunamis that
are several kilometers high
and it's going to cause
storms that are supersonic or hypersonic
in nature
and tsunamis that move faster than the
speed of sound supersonic tsunamis that
are several kilometers high
the entire atmosphere will will go we
will burn for a while you will have
sulfuric acid rain and various other
kinds of acid rain uh you will have
earthquakes that will that will go like
way of the richter scale yeah the entire
planet will ring like a like a bell you
will have tsunamis that circle the globe
multiple times multiple times multiple
times you'll have storms that are
unimaginable
then you will have a nuclear winter a
decade two decades or so and
for some time the entire atmosphere will
become
like you know boiling hot it's
it's
unimaginable that anything will survive
but some species of animals
or microorganisms or whatever will
certainly survive it's going to be a
very difficult and long and hard nuclear
winter or asteroid impact winter
eventually life will rebound after a few
million years maybe 10 million years or
so that will happen but if we are around
when this happens it's well it's
curtains essentially
because even if we survive that the
planet will be unrecognizable
that's what happens
so the best thing is to keep a very very
very close watch on these naughty
planets that come so close to us and if
there is any indication there's any
that it could come too close to us for
comfort then we need to take steps
well in advance decades in advance yep
so uh
yeah so that's about this guy this comet
smith tuttle swift turtle why am i
saying smith
so this was last seen in 1992. there
were a couple of other comets very
interesting comets in the 1990s there
was one in 1996 called yakutake
um that i saw myself when i was a kid
very
pretty comet to see then there was one
called hail bop which came in 1997
and both these comets were very
visible comets very bright comets uh
hail bop
has a period of about 2 500 years so it
will not reappear for another two and a
half millennia and cometh yakutake which
is very bright and very pretty it has a
period of i think about 70 000 years so
it will reappear close to us in about 70
000 years time these are called long
period comments
uh our comment over here swift turtle is
not a long period comment just 130
something years 133 years so that is uh
pretty soon for a comet to reappear and
of course there if you want to know what
a cometary impact looks like
you should look back to the event of
1994 the impact of comet shoemaker levi
which
was torn to pieces by the gravity of
jupiter in 1992 it broke apart and then
a couple of years later in 1994 it hit
jupiter bang bang bang bang bang the
different
bits of the comet the pieces of the
comet impacted jupiter one after the
other and that's been captured on on on
camera
you can google that what the image okay
let's take a look at that what it looks
like shall we uh shoemaker leave a
impact shoe maker
lee by impact let's see what that looks
like if you want to see what that is
like it was a
yeah you can see this massive scar on
the side of jupiter now here you can see
the impacts the flashes of the impact
yeah multiple impacts on jupiter so it's
the first time we ever captured on photo
on camera
uh
the impact of the collision of one solar
system object with another
and you can see it was massive so this
is the kind of thing that would we would
have experienced
66 million years ago
during the chichalub
impact
which which changed the world forever
right so to summarize this is happening
in
twenty 2126 it's gonna come close to us
about 70 times the earth moon distance
hopefully not closer than that and most
likely we're not going to have an impact
but if there is an impact it's gonna
end the world as we know it and the plan
and transform the planet completely yeah
okay this is an extraordinarily long
question of first of all a request to
all my dear viewers my esteemed viewers
please keep your questions short this
one is a whole bunch of questions
interesting questions that's why i've
taken it i typically see questions like
this paragraphs long i just don't take
them because it will take a long time
just to read it out but i'm taking this
because it's
a bunch of interesting questions
right
let me see it's quite small the
goldilocks zone is defined as the
distance between a star to support water
at most the gold lock zone for any star
is that region from the star at a
certain distance from the start where
liquid water can exist on a planet that
is the simple definition of goldilocks
zone it has nothing to do with
atmospheric pressure the distance from
the star where liquid water can exist
uh and
so on okay so what is the first question
can life develop on a planet with
different gravity than ours under
circles certain circumstances circum
certain conditions
uh secondly what would be the effects of
periodic tidal gravity in a binary
system
presence of a larger planet nearby
on the development of life on a planet
thirdly what about a hypogravity world
without surface water what's the
presence of subterranean water and
atmosphere okay you'll wear must be
turning its grip okay okay okay okay all
of that so
can life develop on a planet with
different gravity than ours yes
yes why do we think there could have
been life on mars mars has a different
gravity than ours it's the gravity there
is much
lesser than the gravity on earth but
mass is a prime candidate for life
having existed in the past because of
the
presence in the past of flowing water
large bodies of water on mars so yes
that's that's a great example mars
because there was once lots of flowing
water on the planet even though the
gravity is much less than that of earth
it's a prime candidate for life having
possibly emerged there especially
microbial life microscopic life etc so
yes the answer to question number one is
yes life can certainly develop on a
planet with different gravity than ours
under various conditions
under most conditions yes uh secondly
uh what would be the effects of a
pre-periodic tidal gravity exit on a
binary system
presence of a larger planet nearby etc
you can have life on moons let's say you
have
there are various moons of jupiter
saturn one good example is urine europa
one is ganymede then there is titan
these are not planets these are moons
and there is this presence of this
massive gravitational pull of the of the
of the planet around which the moon is
going in one case there's jupiter in one
case there's saturn so yes there are
tidal forces
there are tidal forces on these planets
that are exerted not only by the
planet
around which the the moon is going but
also the sun the sun also has a tidal
effect so there is a more complex
dynamics on these moons you know tidal
dynamics and yet life can certainly
emerge there
microscopic life doesn't care what sort
of tidal forces are are appearing so if
you have a subsurface ocean on such a
planet yes certainly you could have life
yeah especially
and the thing about these tidal forces
especially if a moon is really close to
the surface to the surface of the mother
planet then you will have very strong
tidal forces these strong tidal forces
can distort the entire shape of the
planet itself periodically and that can
cause internal friction and cause heat
the production of heat deep within the
planet which can actually heat up the
water the subsurface ocean if it exists
and that can
of course
be conducive to life for instance on our
own planet we have these uh thermal
vents
subsurface vents several kilometers
under the oceans
where you have essentially underwater
volcanoes and these underwater volcanoes
produce heat and that heat
is something that is conducive to life
and we find very various strange forms
of life around these uh these thermal
vents geothermal vents under the ocean
so something similar could happen if you
have strong tidal forces that produce
heat deep within the planet yeah or or a
moon yeah and that could heat up the
subsurface oceans
and be conducive to life especially if
the right
molecules and chemistry is also present
in
in the water
third what about a hypogravity world
without surface water but presence of
subterranean water and atmosphere yeah
even if there is no atmosphere if you
have a subterranean ocean like europa
which is a hypogravity world it's a moon
it's much smaller than the earth so you
could call it a hypogravity world or
pluto even pluto may have a subsurface
ocean which may be liquid yes liquid
and so on and there's no atmosphere
there but there's water it it could be
possibly completely dark and yet the if
you have a source of heat and if you
have the right chemistry the right
molecules which may which is possible
then you may have certain kinds of life
primitive life or whatever maybe
bioluminescent light i'm just
speculating yes so the answer to
question number one is yes the answer of
question number two is uh
again i gave it number three also yes so
yeah i hope that explains
uh that answers the questions
okay venue says can you explain the
basics of kalutsak line theory and how
it was a precursor to spring theory and
why was it discredited it's not been
discredited okay what is kalu klein
theory
so we know
okay to understand sarc line theory we
have to understand
dimensions what are dimensions yeah
so
gravitation was for the longest time
understood from the newtonian
perspective as an inverse square force
f is equal to g m one m two upon r
squared right where r squared where r is
the distance between the two
gravitational gravitating bodies
the two masses
so uh that was the newtonian
approximation of what gravity is the
newtonian way of looking at gravity and
it is extremely accurate it is still
very accurate
you can still
launch a rocket send it to the moon
and bring it back with a living
people using just newtonian mechanics so
it's still very accurate now in
the general theory of relativity came
out
uh albert einstein
in which
gravitation was seen as the curvature of
space-time so a new
dimension was introduced the the fourth
dimension the dimension of time yeah and
then gravity
is the curvature of space time and so on
mass tells space time how to curve and
the curvature of space time tells mass
how to move this is geometric dynamics
and so on yeah
so kalooza client theory came around
came out around this time it's like a
few years after the
general theory of relativity now what is
all this about so let's first understand
what are dimensions
dimensions
so let's say i am
i am setting a
let's say i i'm sitting in my office
yeah
and i want
my friend to come there
so i have to give my friend
the location
the location now let's let's uh
one second let me put something on the
screen
let's see what a coordinate grid looks
like yes
this is a coordinate grid
the x-axis and the y-axis so let's say
you superimpose this on the map of a
city
and let's say all of these lines yeah
the horizontal lines and the vertical
lines are streets of the city so instead
of giving names to my streets i'm going
to give numbers to my streets yes
so the horizontal lines are streets that
are lying in the east-west direction
and the vertical lines are streets that
are
in the north-south direction so let's
say i tell my friend that i am at the
building
that is at the interac intersection
of the fourth no of the fourth
north south street in the third east
west street
so then my friend will have the exact
location of where my building is where
my office is located so i have given two
dimensions
i have given my location in two
dimensions to my friend and that is an
exact location but what if i am sitting
on the 18th floor of my building then i
will also have to specify one more
location to my friend one more
coordinate one more dimension
the third dimension that i am on the
18th floor not on the ground floor so
now i have provided my friend three
different
dimensions length breadth and height
yes
but
what if i am available only at 3 pm in
my office
i won't be there at 3 5 so i want my
friend to come to these three coordinate
dimensions these three coordinates
exactly at 3 p.m so that is the fourth
dimension i'm now offering
the fourth dimension the dimension of
time
so the thing about the the three spatial
dimensions
is that you can revisit them anytime you
want but time is something that flows
and times is something time is something
you cannot revisit
yeah
it's something that's only
controllable in the future so you can be
so at some place in the future at a
certain time but you can't be at that
place in the past at a certain time
so these are the four dimensions that we
know of the four space time dimensions
the three dimensions of space and one
dimension of time now what did kaluza
incline do
they said what if there is a fourth
spatial dimension so in general
relativity there are four dimensions
three
space dimensions once one one time
dimension kaluza incline it's a long
story how the entire theory developed
but what they essentially said is what
if there is the fourth spatial dimension
which brings the total number of
dimensions to five
but then the question is if there is a
fourth dimension of space why don't we
see it
we only see three dimensions
why don't we see it so they said what if
this is a microscopic dimension what see
if you're okay let me show you the map
again
and let's go to uh to the earth
so here we are
uh let me share that i'm sorry one
second give me a second to share it on
the screen
here is the the earth
so let's say i am sitting on the equator
of the earth and i start walking east or
let's say i sit on a plane
rocket plane very fast and i go east so
i'm starting over here at this point
right beneath this the southernmost
point of india i'm going east i'll keep
going east keep going east keep going
east keep going east keep going east
keep going east a little more and i am
back where i began
so kaluzan klein said what if there are
dimensions that are ultra microscopic in
scale
and they are curled up in such in such a
form that they
reconnect with themselves
so a dimension that is circular
essentially in shape
you start at one point one one place in
the dimension you go and you will end up
in the same place what if you have these
ultra compactified dimensions and what
if the fourth spatial dimension s p a t
i a l spatial dimension is an ultra
compact dimension that is curled up onto
itself
yeah so let's say you you make a circle
but you make it so small that it just
looks like a point
that sort of thing
so from far away it looks like a point
so maybe there is a fourth space spatial
dimension but it is so small and so
curled up that we don't observe it
with the senses that we we possess maybe
it is let's say a millionth of the size
of an atom of a hydrogen atom how about
that
so that's what they
proposed
they said what if we do this what if we
introduce a fourth dimension and total
fifth dimension here
and let's see what the math tells us
what what will the properties of the
universe be like if there is a fourth
dimension of space so they worked out
the math and they found that
the force of gravity
what we perceive as gravity in in
general relativity when you introduce a
fifth dimension like this
the effect of gravity in this fifth
dimension
is that it produces what we call
electromagnetism
so even though this dimension is so
small so compact
and essentially
undetectable to us if such of fifth
dimension exists
then it is
this the effect of gravity in this
dimension that will generate what we
what we feel the force that we call
electromagnetism
so those
materials
that are affected by electromagnetism
they move in this dimension and whatever
is not affected by it does not move and
so on so that is kaluth line theory
and this remained like a mathematical
curiosity oddity artifact for the
longest time it was like very
interesting but what do you do with it
and then string theory appeared
1960s onwards 50s 1960s i believe and
then they took kalooza klein the kaluzak
klein idea and they extended it the
thing about string theory is that the
theory itself predicts how many
dimensions of space time should exist it
says there are 10 dimensions 10
dimensions in total so this was
essentially something that took the
khaluzakline formalism
further ahead in in a certain way
and then again those extra dimensions
are uh
they are compactified dimensions just
like kalooza kind and
had thought so that is how so that is
what kalooza klein theory is
that is how it was the precursor to
string theory string theory extended
that idea further and and borrowed the
concept of compactified dimensions from
the khaluzakan theory it's never been
discredited it still is something that
you should study if you're a physicist
here
it's a very interesting thing i mean
the the the force of electromagnetism
emerges out of the out of the fifth
collusion
dimension it is the effect of gravity in
this dimension that gives off gives rise
to what we perceive as electromagnetism
that is what this theory says it's
obviously
not a complete theory yeah it's been
extended into what we call string theory
but string theory itself is far from
perfect but these
theories which may not be completely
perfect and not be complete
give us ideas about how we can proceed
further in in
in trying to tackle the big problems and
big missing pieces of the jigsaw puzzle
when it comes to physics because we
understand very little of the universe
even now and we need to delve deeper
into it so
so yeah that's what it is it's never
been discredited
it's it's uh it's been extended further
and many of the ideas were borrowed and
incorporated into string theory so it's
not a theory that's been discredited
it's a beautiful theory it's i think
every student of theoretical physics
should study it
all right
bavish says if we can't beat the speed
of light then how do the ufos if they
are real
reach the earth from alien planets hmm
good question i like it there
so the closest
star system
to us
is the proxy is is proxima centauri
which is roughly four point something
light years from here which means that
if i shine a laser beam at proxima
centauri it will take four or so about
four years to reach there that light
yeah
so
uh
and if you use a chemical rocket
or a light cell technology or whatever
at one tenth of the speed of light let's
say you use light sail technology that
can accelerate your spacecraft to 30 of
the speed of light even at that speed it
will take 30 to 40 years to reach
proxima centauri and if you use your
good old chemical rockets it will take
hundreds of thousands of years to reach
there so that's how big and vast and
vast and empty space is
so let's say you have aliens who have
these
craft spacecraft which we call ufos
and let's say the ufos actually exist
let's say hypothetically we're not sure
but
let's say the ufo phenomenon is a real
alien spacecraft
then the question is that most likely
there's no guarantee that proxima
centauri is where they're coming from
they could be coming from much further
away from within our galaxy or maybe
from beyond our galaxy who knows so
maybe they're traveling hundreds of
light years to come here maybe thousands
of light years maybe millions we don't
know
so if we can't beat the speed of light
it means that they would have taken
millions of years to reach thousands of
years i mean that doesn't make sense
because usually as far as you know
biological lifetimes are short
so how do they do it are they so patient
i mean if they have long lifetimes are
they so patient they will wait so long
so
so how do these ufos reach
our planet will reach the united states
from alien planets
so let's examine various scenarios first
the first scenario is the simplest
scenario that they don't exceed the
speed of light they come at sub-light
speeds maybe 10 percent the speed of
light maybe 30 of the speed of light and
maybe the aliens who travel in these
spacecraft they have extremely long life
life spans perhaps
maybe each alien can live let's say 10
000 years in the spend a thousand years
coming here which means that they are
spending 10 of their lifetime in on a
one-way trip
let's say they are willing to make the
investment of time
so that is one possibility maybe the the
trip takes 10 000 maybe the trip takes a
thousand years one way
and maybe they are willing to make the
investment of time which is a very
implausible scenario but let's there is
one one scenario one one possibility
the second possibility is that they
don't
they cheat
they cheat cheating they do cheating
they don't travel through space time
at faster than the speed of light they
make holes in space time and they use
what we call wormholes
to to take a shortcut between two very
far away regions of space time
so i've spoken about wormholes multiple
times these are like
einstein frozen bridges yeah
and well the physics says that it's it's
the wormholes don't want to stay open
they want to snap shut and they will
snap shut and create two singularities
which are black holes or white holes
black holes most likely so wormholes
can exist
yeah
according to physics it's allowed but
they want to snapshot they won't don't
want to stay open so then how do you
keep verbal wormholes open you may have
to put some exotic matter in our mold
that will prevent it from closing maybe
negative mass
that will repel the walls the throat of
the wormhole and keep it open that's one
possibility secondly you may have to
insert
or you may have to make use of the
hypothetical cosmic strings topological
defects that were left over from the
beginning of the birth of the universe
possibly that
so maybe aliens have discovered these
cosmic springs and they've built
wormholes around that so that the
wormhole simply can't close shut
and then they would use that
and that's a possibility so maybe they
have they have discovered wormhole
technology
so they may live on a distant galaxy
maybe a billion light years away but
they know these humans are there and you
won't visit them they want to pay them
with it so they create a warm hole they
open it
and they they take the shortcut
and instead of a billion years to reach
here at the speed of light it takes them
three weeks
traveling through the world mall yeah
maybe
so that's the other possibility the
third possibility is that they have
invented warp drives
what drives are when you
essentially sit in a bubble of space
time that itself moves faster than the
speed of light and in a in a way that
does not break the laws of physics
so warp drive technology hypothetically
it may be possible
alcubia drive and various other
solutions of einstein's field equations
which may alive allow warp drive
technology to exist if you can well make
it happen which is way way beyond our
capabilities but maybe the aliens have
it and maybe they use warp drive drives
like in star trek yeah so one
possibility is that they actually come
they actually travel at speeds much
lower than the speed of light and they
take a very long time to reach it that's
possibility one possibility two is that
they have wormhole technology and they
can appear here in a matter of days or
weeks from billions of ideas away and
thirdly they may have
warp drive technology
so these are the three possibilities i
can think of
and obviously they seem to love the us
great country in the world and they all
come to the u.s and they bypass all
other countries so yeah
that's what i can
offer you in terms of possibilities and
scenarios
next question
okay
says
if we have explored only five percent of
the oceans then is there a possibility
of finding a trench deeper than the
mariana trench
got the question let's put map
where's the map
here's the map so where is the mariana
trench let's put the satellite imagery
oh clouds i don't want clouds i want
trenches so let's dig deeper let's go to
the philippines
philippines yeah
so where is the mariana trench it will
be somewhere around here can you see
these deep trenches
these are at the edges of various
tectonic plates where tectonic plates
you have subduction zones etc and this
is where you have volcanism and
earthquakes and stuff like that so let's
search for the mariana trench
m-a-r-i-a-n-a
space
t-r-e-n-c-h it will be somewhere there
where i saw where i went
okay where is it zuma
zoom out bro
yeah close to where i was here it is
so the mariana trench is known to be the
deepest point in the oceans anywhere on
the planet
and it's near guam near the philippines
the kaolin islands near palau and so on
so
it's at the intersection of these two
zones and if you go if you look here
it's like a deep deep deep trench
yeah like you have in mountains a deep
trench so that's where it is it's it's
most likely it is mostly it is it is
definitely
the deepest point
that we know of in the
oceans on our planet so the question is
if we have explored only five percent of
the oceans
is there a possibility of finding a
trench deeper than the mariana trench i
think the possibility is
is definitely
it's a thing but it's not it's a remote
possibility when i say that we have
explored only five percent or so of the
oceans it means that we have explored
only five percent of the life forms and
all that on the oceans but we have a
very good idea of the subsurface
sub-ocean topology
of the planet and it has been very
necessary to map out all the ocean
floors in great detail
because of submarines
various countries operate submarines for
military purposes the u.s the ussr used
to do it now that you have russia then
you have the chinese you have the north
koreans you have india also operating
submarines and to operate submarines you
need to know the ocean floor in
extremely great detail otherwise you're
going to run into an
into a subsurface mountain or something
you don't want that to happen
so
we have extremely detailed maps of the
surface of the ocean
we know what the surface of the ocean
looks like
on maps
but nobody is actually gone there
right nobody actually gone there and
seen on the surface of the oceans and
seen seen what lives there what sort of
life is there and all that so we have
detailed maps
very reliable detail maps of the of this
of the bottom of the oceans
and yet we don't know what is there we
know what is the geography what is the
topology what are the topological
features how tall the mountains are how
deep the trenches are and so on but we
don't know what is there
that's what i mean by we haven't
explored much of the oceans
right so most likely this itself is the
deepest point
in
the oceans most likely if we find
something else to be deeper deeper than
the marine trench i will be very
surprised so that's what i meant by we
have explored only five percent or so of
the oceans
means how deep have we gone what kind of
life have we observed and stuff like
that
most of the subsurface world is unknown
so over here also we have this so
essentially when you have islands they
are the tops of inch of underwater
mountains
the andaman islands are
the tops of these massive mountains that
sit on the surface of the ocean that
rise from the surface of the ocean
the luxury pylons are again
the
topmost parts of these subsurface
oceans that rise from the surface of
the planet under the oceans and the same
goes for the maldives and other places
right
right so that in short is the answer
most likely we will not discover any
other place that is deeper than the
marina trench most likely
okay ali says when it come no what comes
after the silicon processors currently
we are in the phase of five nanometer
silicon processors and soon three
nanometer silicon processors will be
available what comes next when
traditional silicon chips reach their
maximum capacity around one or two
uh around one nanometer or two silicon
atoms will there be another new material
for processors or some kind of change
and silicon has more potential
uh is there any way to use quantum
computing for usual daily use like
graphics gaming etc lots of questions
okay let's talk about silicon processors
and what comes next
so when we talk about silicon processors
microprocessors and on these chips and
all that
we are talking about transistors
we are placing transistors on silicon
chips silicon wafers
so these assemblies of transistors are
we're packing lots and lots enormous
numbers of transistors in very small
very small into a very small surface
area
right
and
so that's what a microprocessor is
that's what a silicon
wafer silicon chip is it's
all these electric electronic circuits
all these transistors
massive numbers of transistors on a very
small surface area
and according to moore's low the
computing power computing the
the maximum computing power
is said to double every two years or so
right and that's what the trend has been
thus far but we are now reaching the
limits of the capabilities of silicon
processors because we are going we are
going
to almost the atomic level
and when we reach the scale of just a
couple of atoms or so
uh what we are doing is we are using
electrons
in all of this right we are
all of the data that we have
is
stored on these silicon
chips and it's in the form of
electrical pulses so all the data
transport happens in the form of
electrical pulses all the processing all
the computing it is all in the form of
electrical pulses it's electrons that we
are using
and when you pack so much so many
transistors into such a small place and
when when you do the processing heat is
generated heat
so the
we know our computers become hot our
phones become hot because of all this
heat that is generated as a byproduct of
all this processing that we do using
electrical pulses right now when you go
deep down into the atomic level to the
scale of
two nanometers one nanometer yeah when
you go down to the scale of just a few
atoms
there are certain limitations that you
encounter first of all when you're using
electrons to do all this processing
you run into this process this this
problem called
quantum tunneling it's a quantum
phenomenon in which electrons do things
you don't want them to do
they go through walls
and you don't want them to go through
walls so what you have is copper wires
and electrical pulses that's what we are
using on these silicon processors and we
are now coming very close to the limits
so the other material that you can think
of is germanium
i think the first
first such processor was actually a
germanium processor you know it was
it was built on germanium
on a german intro germanium chip
germanium is also a very good
semiconductor right the thing
is that silicon was then adopted as the
standard because silicon is readily
available germanium is not that readily
available and then all the technology
was built over the past 40 50 years on
silicon wafers
so we know really well how to use
silicon germanium if you if you switch
to germanium uh
i'm not sure if you will be able to get
better results and go further deep but
you will have to reinvent many of these
technologies from scratch because it's
an art as well as a science yeah
that's what technology is
so uh
so that's why we have stuck to silicon
so now we are reaching the limits we're
gonna soon run into the problem of
electron tunneling tunneling through war
or through walls that's what happens and
then that will give us results we don't
want
then there's also the process of the
problem of heat so one solution is you
take
thus far we have two-dimensional
uh circuits two-dimensional
microprocessors what if you make them
three-dimensional you take a silicon
chip
with all the uh circuits etched onto it
and you stack up these silicon chips
so instead of a two-dimensional square
processor you have a three-dimensional
cubicle processor cube it's a cube and
you can
pack in so much more circuits into that
the problem is that of heat
how do we manage the heat just a small
two-dimensional silicon processor
produces so much heat it's really really
tough to keep a computer cool
if you make it three-dimensional it's
going to produce an incredible amount of
heat it may burn up the circuit it will
melt things
and that's not what we want
so that's the problem we will face
when we have three dimensional processes
the other possibility is to use is to
ditch electrons altogether and go to
photons photonics
so when it comes to photonics
you're all aware of
fiber optics
these photon pulses here light pulses
that we use for transmitting data uh
internet internet data and all that so
you could
possibly ex one could possibly explore
ditching the uh
electron altogether and transitioning to
photons photonics so photonic circuits
but that is something that could
possibly happen but it's it's a long way
off
other materials you could use instead of
silicon and germanium could be carbon
nanotubes
or graphene
graphene is a
is
sheets of carbon
nanotubes carbon nanotubes are so what
you do in nanotubes is that you take
carbon atoms you arrange them in this
hexagonal shape
you create a
surface you know two dimensional surface
and you roll it up
so then you get these very thin
very thin uh
tubes called carbon nanotubes that could
be a few microns long and they have very
good semiconductor properties and they
are good great properties that could be
very very useful for computing but once
again that is still something that could
be at least a decade or so off
yeah so yeah these are possibilities
that exist that will be explored
graphene also has potential but it also
has problems because graphene
it gets damaged easily and you have to
use it on some other material it has to
be placed properly on the material you
you
create a strip of graphene you take it
and you put it somewhere else it gets
damaged and you could have holes in it
and if you have holes in it you can
do computing properly and various things
so there are limitations there are
problems the problems will eventually
have to be overcome in one way or the
other so one possibility is germanium
one possibility is carbon nanotubes one
possibilities graphene
uh you could even switch all switch over
to photonics instead of electrons so
light based computing photon based
computing instead of electron based
computing so in that case you will we
will be able to ditch
copper wires
and silicon wafers and you would have
fiber optics possibly possibly and
there's even more exotic things like dna
based computers or something you know
it's possible to store data in a
synthetic dna now is it possible to
use it for computing
maybe maybe so that's something that's
even more
you know
left field than what what i've just
discussed but yeah some of these are
some of the possibilities that are being
taken seriously not quite dna based
computing but carbon nanotubes graphene
carbon nanotubes cubes graphene
germanium and photonics that's what i
can think of off the top of my head
but we are certainly like you say ali
that we are certainly reaching the
limits the the
limits
of what silicon can offer us and sooner
rather than later we're gonna have to
make some changes in if we want to
continue
uh having more and more powerful
computers and for more slow to
still apply
okay they just says can ai artificial
intelligence replace jobs in creative
fields so people have asked me questions
about ai stealing jobs and taking over
jobs yeah that's that's definitely going
to happen but this is a different kind
of question can ai replace jobs in
creative fields
jobs such as content writers graphic
designers digital artists is ai
unethical how can people save themselves
from being jobless in the coming ten to
five years let's focus on the creative
aspect of the question unethical
technology is a tool
a stick
is a tool
a stick can be used for ethical purposes
and unethical purposes nuclear power can
be used for ethical purposes and
unethical purposes technology is a moral
it is there is no good or bad right or
wrong in technology it all depends on
how it is used so ai is it unethical no
it's not unethical it's just a
technology it all depends on how we use
it the people who use it will either be
ethical or unethical the uses will
either be ethical or unethical the
technology is is
a purpose agnostic it is a moral it's
not immoral or moral it's a moral it has
no morality it's just technology now
going back to the real question
can ai replace jobs in creative fields
yes
so what we are finding now is that ai
has most likely already
passed the turing test what is the
turing test it's when you have two black
boxes
behind one black box is an actual human
being behind the other black box is a
machine a computer an ai whatever you
want to call it and you have a
conversation in some form with both the
black boxes and when
your ai
can have a conversation with an actual
human being and the human being can't
tell whether it's a human or a machine
that's when the ai has passed the turing
test and most likely from the
news that's leaking out of google etc it
looks like the google ai
uh what it's called lambda is it it
looks like it has definitely passed the
turing test so we have breached that
wall most likely yeah so we are now in
the post turing test era
ai's have
i'm not saying it's become sentient or
conscious but it's certainly able to
converse conversationally
in real time with a human human being in
a way that you can't tell if it's human
or not it looks like you like a proper
human being no different from a human
being so that's what's already happened
now
we are also
seeing all these new ais that come that
are appearing you give the ai a bunch of
text
you describe what you want the ai to
paint it will produce a digital painting
for you and some of these digital
paintings are incredibly beautiful and
you can't tell that it's not a human
being that's produced it
yeah
so we are already
at the stage
where
ai can replace content writers it's able
to create text that looks just like it's
been written by a human being in a
well-educated human being at that yeah
so high quality content based on various
keywords it's able to produce
so it can we have we have reached the
stage where ai could very soon start
replacing content writers yeah the
services will soon be available for
subscription pay ten dollars a month and
you will be able to produce any kind of
content you want original content
yeah that will pass any plagiarism test
so that is there graphic design very
soon you'll have ai we already have ai
that's producing incredible art
so maybe painters graphic designers
digital artists could also be challenged
by that i mean it would take somebody
like pablo picasso or or vincent van
gogh
weeks possibly a week or so maybe two
weeks maybe a month to produce a high
quality work of art these ais can spit
that out in in seconds 10 seconds 20
seconds 50 seconds 60 seconds right
so soon enough you will have a
proliferation of these digital works of
art from ais
so the answer to your question there
just is that yes ai can certainly
replace jobs in the creative creative
fields
it is already reached the stage where we
we will have artificial intelligence
generated content high quality content
sales letters newsletters what not yeah
even novels who knows it's possible
and digital art as well yeah so that's
where we are how can people save
themselves from being jobless in the
coming 10 to 15 years by
by acquiring skills that ai can't crack
um so what are examples of that well you
can become an athlete in a i can't be an
athlete yeah
you can be a leader ais can't be leaders
as far as i know
uh who knows even that could so
we will have to think creatively
and whatever
fields
or jobs
are such that ai can perform them
those will be replaced soon enough
so that's where
the people who are
part of those fields are the ones who
will be at threat
of being replaced and being rendered
redundant
so i think it's about acquiring new
skills
and staying on top of your game and
going into fields that ai cannot
penetrate
so that's where we are right now
divya says what do you think of the
artemis missions is it necessary to send
people to the moon because it involves
so much money and risk
is there a solid reason to do that
if it is not important to send people to
the moon where do you think the money
should be invested instead i
okay
500 years ago
the europeans started undertaking this
incredibly expensive and risky voyages
across the oceans
christopher columbus
he
built these four ships
the money for that
voyage was given by the king and queen
of spain
they made a substantial investment into
this incredibly
risky venture that this guy proposed to
them and
he he promised them that there will be
gold at the end of the of the journey
right
uh
so there is a lot of risk involved in
any new exploration any venture that
involves
exploration 500 years ago the oceans
were the frontier that the europeans
knew about we in india already knew
about it but the europeans they were
exploring oceans it was very risky it it
cost a lot of money to build ships to
pay for all these journeys to to hire
men to
man the ships and so on
now we are going across
planets we're going to the moon we want
to go to the ma to to mars yeah so this
is the new frontier space is the new
frontier so we have space ships we have
rockets and yes they cost money
it is risky in the past you went went to
sea on a ship you could drown the ship
could be sunk it could be lost in a
storm it could hit a piece of rock that
you may not be able to see
and many people died as a result you
find shipwrecks all across the ocean
floors
it's a risk
is the risk worth it it's for
well it's for you to decide
so it's all about balancing risk and
reward
what is the reward that i may possibly
get
for and for taking this risk
right
the risk essentially is calculated in
terms of dollars
and human lives also are
obviously they are at stake but the
planners who plan this they typically
think in terms of dollars human lives we
have we have how many seven eight
billion humans a few here and there they
will not really care about
at the top level so the risk versus
reward calculation is done and
the question is
when christopher columbus went out to
look for india they all knew that india
was incredibly fabulously wealthy so
they expected that christopher columbus
if he succeeds he will be able to bring
back gold for us that's what the kingdom
and queen of spain had calculated and
that's why they decided to fund his
venture
now when it comes to going to the moon
what do we get there there's no gold on
the moon so what is there there are
other things
the moon may be
is known to be
rich in various minerals its composition
is in some ways similar to that of the
earth
so there is mineral wealth there is a
lot of water there which is valuable in
space
and then there is the lunar regolith
which contains an which is known to have
us an abundance of a certain
isotope
of helium
which
could be
uh extremely valuable as a next
generation nuclear fuel
so the and of course there is territory
right now the moon belongs to nobody but
once people start going that they will
start claiming territory for themselves
and demarcating territory so yeah
territory is obviously valuable real
estate is valuable anywhere in the world
anywhere in the universe yeah
so these are the reasons why people
are interested in doing this
and of course the the the um there's
also the thought that humanity should
have multiple homes not just our planet
because what if we mess up this parent
which is kind of silly but that's also
one of the arguments they make so
it is not necessary to send people to
the moon but it's desirable
and mars as well because there are
resources out there there is real estate
out there you want people to i mean you
you want
your nation to be among the first ones
to go and exploit and explore these
resources and to to
let's say stake claim on more territory
beyond our planet right
there are financial considerations there
are military considerations there are
geopolitical constitution considerations
and all that humanity has always been
a migratory species we have always been
explorers
so this is part of our nature
so is it necessary to send people to
other places no but it's gonna happen
it's always gonna happen if we don't do
it somebody else will do it and we'll be
left behind so it's always about getting
there getting there being among the
first to get there why did the space
race happen
because the americans and
the soviets
wanted to be the first and at the
forefront of this the the soviets were
the first to launch the sputnik
satellite and the americans went into a
state of panic because they could see
the satellite circling the planet they
could hear it beeping and they said what
if the soviets placed nukes on
satellites they'll be able to rain down
nukes on us at on demand whenever they
want so that's why we also need to get
into this game so the americans and the
soviets are the space race it culminated
with the moon landings
and so on
so when one nation does this everybody
else whoever is capable will try and
catch up and possibly
overtake surpass the achievements of the
other nation that's just the nature of
geopolitical competition so it's not
necessary but it's going to happen yeah
and there are lots of solid reasons like
i've just given you
um
so i think it is indeed important for
india let's let's me let me speak from
india's perspective it is indeed
important for india not to be left
behind in this matter in the space race
in the moon race
in the mars race because
the technologies that you develop
in the process of building these these
machines these rockets and space
exploration and all that they help you
in a variety of other ways all these
various spin-offs of space technology
they are all over all around us and we
don't realize that yeah
and of course these technologies also
have a military dimension
so if you
invest in a robust
top level space program it's going to
benefit you in ways civilians can't even
imagine you it will benefit your nation
right
so that's why it is important for india
to do that
uh india needs to ensure that it's not
left behind
at the end of the 21st century
the two or three nations that lead the
world in space exploration are going to
be the 203 nations that lead the world
and rule the world
so the question indians should ask
themselves is do you want to rule or do
you want to be ruled by somebody else i
think we have had enough of being ruled
by others yes thousand years
approximately i think it's enough
please decide it's enough
so india needs to be at the forefront of
that even nasa is being asked questions
that we are entering a recession we have
inflation why are you spending on space
exploration it has to be done
everything has to happen in parallel yes
india is still a third world nation its
economy is still growing it will keep
growing but we we also need to invest in
space exploration it is imperative that
we are not left behind
so i think it is important to
be
to participate in the space race it's
important to be at the forefront the top
three of the space race send people to
the moon send peer send people to mars
build more powerful rockets do all that
doesn't matter if it costs money yeah
so the second part of the question is
that the answer to that is there is that
it it is important to do that and that
money should be invested into space
exploration
we knew my dear friend again today is
venus day so what is the difference
between chemical physics
and physical chemistry
well actually they're quite similar but
they're different
so what is chemical physics chemical
physics is when you apply the laws and
principles of physics to understood
chemistry to connect to chemicals to
understand how chemistry works yeah you
apply quantum mechanics statistical
matter mechanics uh atomic physics and
molecular physics condensed matter
physics and all these various
disciplines and subfields of physics
into chemistry so let's say you want to
understand why
you know you know what water is right
what is the chemical formula of water
it's h2o
so why is water h2o why did two hydrogen
atoms come together with an oxygen atom
and form a water molecule why is it so
to understand why it is so you have to
actually understand quantum physics or
or atomic physics yeah and to understand
atomic and molecular physics you have to
understand quantum physics so
a hydrogen atom
is a proton the nucleus is a single
proton and typically a hydrogen atom in
the most common isotope has a single
electron that goes around the nucleus
you knock off the electron you ionize
the hydrogen atom it becomes a single
proton it's a hydrogen ion ion right
it's positively charged it's a naked
positive charge and to neutralize that
you have to give it an electron you can
share the electron with something else
with another atom so that's how that's
the basic principle behind the formation
of
compounds of
chemical compounds like h2o and all that
so to understand
chemistry at this level you have to
apply the laws of atomic physics
molecular physics
quantum mechanics
to
understand the properties of chemical
substances you may have to understand
statistical mechanics and condensed
matter physics and so all that so all of
this
this is essentially a bottom-up approach
you're studying chemical processes
you're studying chemical reactions from
the point of view of pure physics so
that is chemical physics right now what
is physical chemistry it's it's
and once again about uh
about chemical physics uh one of the sub
branches
of quantum chemistry
one of the sub branches is quantum
chemistry so you
study chemistry not from the point of
view of molecular physics or atomic
physics but from the pov point of view
of quantum physics and so on now when it
comes to
physical chemistry
so physical chemistry is is the study of
the large scale
macroscopic properties of chemical
substances and chemical systems so
you're studying the the properties you
know if it's a solid what are the
properties of the solid is it
crystalline in nature is it amorphous is
it something else at what is the boiling
point what is the what is the boiling
point of this thing what is the what is
the vaporization point of the the
substance why is it this way is it
ferromagnetic is it something else and
so on so forth the large scale
macroscopic properties of chemical
substances chemicals and chemical
systems that is physical chemistry
that is not chemical physics yeah two
different things but there is some
overlap between the two and um
physical chemists and
and and
i mean the the scientists who study and
work in these two fields have some
things in common and they can certainly
have interesting conversations with
common interests together right
so that's the difference and the
similarities between physical chemistry
and chemical physics
captain burp says two questions firstly
what's a cryogenic engine what are the
working principles and why is depleted
uranium used in tank shells
and other things and not radioactive
when used okay
okay
what is a cryogenic engine a cryogenic
engine is a rocket engine now what do we
mean by cryogenic
cryogenic means something that has very
low temperatures so a cryogenic engine
is an engine that uses
cryogenic fuels fuels that have very
very very low temperatures typically the
cryogenic threshold is
120 kelvin or minus 150 degree
centigrade
yeah
so a fuel
a liquid fuel typically
whose temperature is below 150 below
minus 150 degrees celsius that is a
cryogenic fuel and typically a cryogenic
engine a cryogenic rocket engine uses
cryogenic fuels extremely cold fuels so
the simplest and one of the best
cryogenic engines i mean
two of the best fuels in cryogenic
rockets are liquid oxygen and liquid
hydrogen
you bring bring them together ignite
them they will produce extremely high
temperature steam
so you see various rockets that use
these
fuels liquid oxygen liquid hydrogen they
are essentially giving off water vapor
at extremely high pressures and
temperatures
so the boiling point of hydrogen
is minus 250 degrees celsius
approximately
and the boiling point of oxygen is
approximately minus 180 degrees celsius
so these are two cryogenic fuels so any
rocket engine that uses cryogenic fuels
is called a cryogenic engine now imagine
how difficult it is to build
to to to design and build such an engine
it
uses incredibly low temperature fuel
incredibly low temperatures less than
minus 150 degree celsius and yet it
produces an extremely high pressure high
temperature
flame
exhaust
yeah
so on one so if you have a cryogenic
engine here the fuel flows in from the
top let's say extremely low temperature
and the output is this incredibly high
temperature
jet
of exhaust
and you have to somehow
build an engine
that can handle both kinds of
temperatures
and doesn't explode doesn't blow up
doesn't malfunction so it's it's
extremely hard to do that and that's why
cryogenic rocket technology is something
that is uh
very highly sought after and very few
nations have the
capability of of developing cryogenic
engines
so i don't know how many nations have
developed this the us the ussr now
russia the uk had it they scrapped it
because the americans made them scrap it
the french have it india has it the
the chinese have it the japanese have it
and
yeah as far as i can think of yeah so
these nations have cryogenic rocket uh
cryogenic engine technology so that's
what it is now depleted uranium what is
depleted uranium so when we talk about
uranium let's say we talk about
the natural uranium that we that we are
able to extract out of uranium ore
that
is available naturally in some places so
when we talk about natural uranium it's
about 99.3 percent
uranium-238
it's 99.3
uranium-238 uranium-238 is one kind of
uranium isotope yeah
so natural uranium is 99.3 percent
u238 it is 0.7
roughly
uranium-235 and there's a very small
trace amount of uranium-234
so there are three isotopes uranium-238
uranium-235 and uranium-234
the most abundant isotope 99.27 is
uranium-238
but the one that we want
the one that is valuable is uranium-235
it is the facile isotope of uranium it
is the isotope that is used in nuclear
weapons and nuclear reactors so when you
have reactor grade uranium it's about
five percent it has about five percent
uranium-235 when you have highly
enriched uranium it's about it's more
than 20 percent uranium-235 and when you
have weapons grade uranium it's 90 or
more uranium-235
right so it's a very rare isotope but we
need lots of that to have
a weapons grid uranium now what is
depleted uranium
in depleted uranium you have less than
0.3 percent uranium-235 so you don't
want the fissile isotope you want the
non-fissile isotope you want it to be
mostly
uranium-238 so depleted uranium has less
than 0.3 percent uranium 235 okay it's
it's very high density material it's
almost
twice as dense as lead so lead in case
you have ever
seen
lead it's a very dense
metal
very
heavy a small piece of lead if you try
to lift it up you'll be shocked at how
heavy it is yeah it'll be just this size
you try to lift it up it'll be like what
what is this how is it so heavy
so
lead is very dense and lead is typically
used for uh
as a radiation shield in physics labs
and
medical
labs etc
so urine so depleted uranium is almost
twice as dense is lead and that's why it
is also used for radiation shielding
when you have high intensity gamma rays
other things like that
so one of the uses of depleted uranium
is for radiation shielding that is a
civilian use but you also have military
uses of uranium of deeply
depleted uranium one of the uses is
armor plating let's say you have a tank
well tanks go into war they have a high
likelihood of being hit by projectiles
so you can use depleted uranium in the
armor plating of tanks especially if you
can angle it at a certain angle then
it's even more effective instead of
having these straight lines i mean the
90 degree angles so arbor plating is one
application one use of depleted depleted
uranium the other use
is armor piercing projectiles
and bunker busting missiles and
projectiles
so because it is so dense
it can uh punch through armor so let's
say once again let's say you have a tank
that doesn't have a depleted uranium
shielding it has your regular steel
shielding or whatever material they use
chobam is it i'm not sure whatever they
use so if you have
a projectile let's say a bullet heavy
caliber bullet or a shell
a tank shell or any other projectile
that has a depleted uranium tip it may
be able to punch through the shielding
or if you have a bunker that is let's
say 10 meters underground yeah
and
one of the evil leaders of the third
world nation
is is hiding under there let's say
was hiding under a bunker if the
americans wanted to take him out and if
they knew the location of the of the
bunker and let's say it's 10 meters
underground so it's shielded by 10
meters of worth or maybe 10 or maybe 20
meters of earth
and maybe it is it is encased in
concrete
even then if you have
a high velocity projectile
with which is made up of depleted
uranium it may be able to punch through
the 10 meters 20 meters of earth and
even punch through
the concrete shielding and explode
inside the bunker
you also have various aircraft hangars
that have that are made up of reinforced
concrete so even if you hit it with with
a tank shell or whatever it may not
destroy the aircraft inside in that case
if you have a depleted uranium
projectile it may be able to punch
through the shielding and destroy the
aircraft inside so these are some of the
uses
of depleted uranium like i said it's
almost twice as dense
as as as lead i think uh overall uranium
natural uranium has a density of about
18 000 or 19 000
kilograms per cubic meter what does it
mean
let's say you
have yourself a cube
made up of
natural uranium
and it is one meter in dimension so one
meter height one meter breadth and one
meter length that sort of cube if you
have a cube of that size made up of
natural uranium it's going to
weigh almost 19 000 kilograms 19 tons
if you have
a cubic meter of water it's going to
only weigh 1000 kilograms compared to 19
000 kilograms of
uranium
iron around 8000 meters gold about 19
000 slightly more than uranium and the
densest element we know of is called
osmium
and if you take a cubic meter of osmium
it weighs about 22 and a half tons
approximately
yeah
so that is what it is that's what
depleted uranium is and that's why it's
used in tanks anti-tank shells and all
that it is not radioactive it has a very
low concentration very low percentage of
the radioactive isotope the fissilizer
of uranium-235 and that's why it is not
it is not a radioactive
anywhere as much as uranium 235
or natural uranium
okay next question
shiva satya says can you please explain
the different black hole type the
different types of black holes
schwarzschild blackhole kerr
uh wrestler nordstrom curry newman
what's the behavior and effect of each
type of black holes in the surrounding
surrounding universe
i may have taken this question in the
past but for the benefit of newer
viewers here we are again
um there are four major types of black
hole the schwarzschild black hole the
reisner nordstrom black hole the curved
black hole and the ker newman black hole
what are the differences between these
two the standard
simplest black hole you can think of is
a schwarzschild black hole it is
an uncharged and non-rotating black hole
yeah
and that is the short shield solution to
the einstein field equations so a
schwarzschild black hole has no charge
and it has no rotation it has no angular
momentum it is a non-rotating uncharged
black hole yeah
a rice
and a schwarzschild black hole is
perfectly spherical
a reisner nordstrom black hole
is also non-rotating it has zero angular
momentum but it is charged it has some
charge
right then there is something called
occur black hole the curve solution to
the field equations that is a rotating
black hole it has angular momentum but
it has no charge
so this is not going to be perfectly
spherical it's going to be oblate it's
like a squashed
sphere that's the shape of this black
hole and then you have the cur newman
solution the current metric which is
a charged black hole that also has
rotation that also has angular momentum
right so these are the four different
types of black holes
now when you have a short street black
hole it has no rotation so it does not
drag space time with it yeah
so when you have a black hole that
rotates it actually drags space time
with it space time is not just curved it
is dragged along with the rotation so
that is the effect it has and that is
something you can study dear further if
you study general relativity so these
are the four different kinds of black
holes and
depending on the charge and the angular
momentum and the lack of it or the
presence of it you may have different
effects on the surrounding
space time and other objects near it so
if you have a black hole with charge
it's gonna
have electromagnetic lines of force
which will affect charged objects in its
vicinity or even far away or even at
infinity and so on
so that in short
is
the answer to the question there are
other types of black holes as well like
there is something called an extremal
black hole so an extremal black hole is
is a black hole that has the minimal
possible mass
compatible with any given charge and
angular momentum so let's say you have a
black hole with a certain charge in a
certain angular momentum
the black hole
with the minimum possible mass
corresponding to that charge in that
angular momentum is an extremely black
hole so that's the extreme case
of
a black hole with those parameters right
it's called an extreme black hole and it
is possible that the entropy of such a
black hole could be equal to zero
possibly possibly
yeah that could be so so these are the
different kinds of black holes
okay
venu
says can you briefly describe the
interior and exterior layers of our sun
why and how is the lower atmosphere of
the sun the chromosphere cooler than the
outer atmosphere the corona
yeah the corona is hotter than the
chromosphere weirdly right okay let's
take a look at the sun let's see what
the layers of the sun look like
sun
layers
and let's put that on the screen
let us put that on the screen so that
you get a
visual representation of what the layers
of the sun look like
okay let's go to images
and let us see the first image what does
it show us so this is roughly the kind
of uh
internal structure of the sun has
so at the center of the sun you have
something called
the core of the sun yes
so the core of the sun is over here
so the core of the sun is about about
200 000 kilometers
in
in radius
and its
temperature is about
what is the temperature the temperature
is about is about 15 to 20 million
degrees centigrade that's how the hot
the core is then you have the radiative
zone which is about 300 000 kilometers
in in radius yeah it is that that's how
thick it is
and its temperature is about 7 million
degrees celsius then you have the
convection zone
the convection zone over here and the
convection zone is about 200 000
kilometers
thick
and its temperature is about 2 million
degrees celsius
then you have the photosphere which is
part of the atmosphere that is only
about 500 kilometers thick
it has a temperature of about four or
five or six thousand degrees celsius
above that you have the
chromosphere
which is about one thousand five hundred
kilometers thick it's got a temperature
of what slightly higher near 8 000
degrees celsius
and then you have the corona the outer
layer of the sun and the corona can go
up to 1 million degrees celsius
ridiculous isn't it so that's how it is
now why is it so now first of all you
have to understand certain things
first of all
we see light coming out of the sun yes
the light that comes out of the sun is
in the form of photons
these photons are born inside the sun in
the inner layers of the sun in the core
of the sun essentially right so the
nuclear reaction that gives rise to
photons that gives birth to photons is
called the proton proton chain it is the
backbone of nuclear fusion within the
sun
it gives off neutrinos gamma rays two
things it also is what see inside the
sun you have plasma ionized hydrogen
it's protons and electrons floating
around in extremely hot temperatures and
very densely packed together right so
then you have this this nuclear reaction
called which is called the proton proton
chain
in which essentially uh is the fusion of
hydrogen into helium yeah
and it gives off neutrons incredible
amounts of neutrinos which we experience
all the time
which we which pass through us all the
time solar neutrinos it also gives gamma
rays produces gamma rays so essentially
every single second
every single second about 5 million tons
of matter
are being converted into energy
in the core of the sun
not every day not every hour every
second 5 million tons of matter are
being converted into energy that energy
eventually makes its way out in the form
of light but the photon
the gamma ray photon that is born inside
the sun
it takes
maybe a hundred thousand years maybe a
million years to come out
because inside the sun the
the the protons and other other
particles are packed so
closely together
that a photon can only travel a
millimeter or two before it hits
a proton and it keeps hitting these
protons it keeps getting absorbed and
re-emitted absorbed and re-emitted it
keeps getting
it keeps hitting all these obstacles
and it it takes an incredibly long
amount of time you can calculate roughly
what the time is for the photon
to come out of the sun it will first be
born inside the core then it will go
into the radiative zone it will spend
thousands of years there
and every time it hits a proton it loses
some energy so gamma rays are the most
energetic photons if you look at visible
light it has a spectrum the red end and
the
violet end right
the red end is low energy light
low energy photons the violet end is
more energetic photons then you have
ultraviolet light width that we can't
see which is which is higher energies
then you have x-rays which are even
higher energies and then gamma rays
which are the highest energy photons so
inside the sun you have the formation of
highest energy photons called gamma rays
these gamma rays undergo incredible
amounts of collisions inside the sun
with protons and other
other
sub-atomic particles mostly protons
this process lasts
thousands maybe hundreds of thousands of
years yeah and it's only about roughly a
hundred thousand years or a million
years afterwards that the photon emerges
out of the
interior part of the sun goes beyond the
convection zone and exits through the
photosphere so so the light that we see
was born hundreds of thousands of years
ago inside the sun but once it exits the
sun it takes about eight minutes to
reach the earth right so that's what we
have then we use so so the atmosphere of
the of the sun
is the photosphere the chromosphere and
the corona
and we are not quite sure
of why it is
that the corona of the sun has a
temperature of about a million degrees
celsius but the photosphere and the
chromosphere are much cooler
photosphere about four or five thousand
degrees celsius the chromosphere may be
seven or eight thousand degrees celsius
celsius so why is the
chromosphere
in the photosphere so much cooler than
the corona so and this is something we
observe not only in the sun but
most stars
seem to also have this phenomenon so the
process is not really well understood
maybe it is because of the uh
because of magnetism the sun it has a
very very powerful magnetic field and
you have these magnetic tornadoes that
that are
that emerge out of the sun maybe it is
the magnetism that is uh heating up the
upper layer of the corona of the sun to
that temperature
maybe uh yeah maybe there is a
possibility so the process is not quite
understood it is still it was first
discovered i think
in the first half of the 20th century
that the corona is much hotter than the
lower levels layers of the atmosphere
so maybe it has something to do with
magnetism
maybe there is some other process that
we don't quite understand but yeah it is
one of the existing
mysteries of the sun
so as you can see even the sun which is
something we see every day we don't
quite understand that as well
as much as we would want to so there is
a mystery right there in front of us
the
temperature of the corona why is it so
much higher we don't know yet
okay summer says what exactly are i
scores how long can they last
so what are ice cores
we have
places on our planet where you have
glaciers
and thick uh
layers of ice
if you go to the arctic circle
most of the land is covered in ice very
thick ice the eyes can be
hundreds of meters thick maybe
kilometers thick you go to antarctica
you have ice sheets that are kilometers
thick most likely
so if you were to drill down into this
ice
using drilling technology then you can
pull out various
sections
cylindrical sections of this ice at
various depths below the surface
yeah these cylindrical sections that are
pulled out
through drilling are called ice cores
yeah
so if you go to antarctica you may have
an ice sheet that is maybe
let's say hypothetically two kilometers
thick
now it is possible to
determine the rate at which
ice
uh
ice sheets
form
so
it's like sedimentation on the planet
you drill under the planet and you see
the cross section you are essentially
looking back in time each layer of
sediment represents a certain time
period of the earth's history similarly
if you go if you drill a ice core
the deeper you go the deeper back in
time you're going
so let's see you drill 100 meters down
and
hypothetically if
you add
10 centimeters of ice per year
hypothetically
and you're drilling 100 meters down
so 10 centimeters per year
which means
in 10 years you will have one meter
and you're drilling
100 meters down so that's a thousand
years
so the ice core that you will get at
that depth of 100 meters will be about a
thousand years old roughly
and
and you can see the effect of seasons
etc on the
ice course you will see various
sediments that are the result of the
various seasonal fluctuations you can
determine how much carbon dioxide was in
the air at that given point in time you
can even detect
unknown volcanic explosions eruptions
yeah in the
in there are there are that leave behind
the signatures in the ice cores and so
on so that is what i scores are
how long do they last they last as long
as the ice sheets last yeah
so that's why scores are important you
can actually go back in time and see how
the climate was 1000 years before today
2000 years before today depending on how
far below the surface you can drill and
that tells you a lot about the history
of our planet the climate of our planet
we can detect volcanic eruptions that
may have happened in the past and you
may even be able to
perhaps determine where they happened
and so on so that is what i scores are
that's why they're important that's why
people
go and study them
and yeah so that's what it is
okay bengal tiger says what is a
shooting star should we ask for wishes
yeah wishes i don't know about but what
is the shooting star let me
show you what a meteor is a shooting
star is a meteor let's put meteors on
the screen meet your
so this is what you see
so if you
have access to a patch of sky
with
low light pollution
if you go there at night and you look at
the sky for one hour you're gonna see
multiple meteors for sure guaranteed
i'm not sure if any of you has done that
i did that as a kid
you spend an hour gazing at the sky when
you don't have light pollution you will
see multiple meteors at least five or
six meteors so this is what a meteor
looks like this is a brilliant example
beautiful example of a meteor this is
obviously a very very bright and large
meteor it's green in color
so a meteor
is a piece of space rock
that enters the atmosphere and burns up
in the atmosphere now why is why does it
glow
it's because meteors typically travel at
very high speeds between 20 to 70
kilometers per second yeah
and because of this extreme speed
when they enter the
atmosphere they produce friction they
encounter the
molecules of air in the atmosphere and
because it's it's traveling so fast it
squeezes the air in front of it and the
squeezing produces heat
very high amounts of heat and that heat
first melts the rock
and then vaporizes it
so typically most of these space rocks
they burn up in the atmosphere only if a
space rock is large enough like
significantly large will it actually
impact
the surface of the planet most of it
burns up it happens all the time all the
time
it's happening right now as you speak
there'll be meteors in the sky
so that is what a meteor is right it's
it's not a shooting i mean it's called a
shooting star colloquially it's a meteor
it's a piece of space rock space debris
that burns up into the atmosphere in the
atmosphere and it has various colors
based on the chemical composition of the
rock itself so the color that you're
seeing here is greenish yeah greenish
bluish that means it's a magnesium
meteor it is a meteor that has a
significant amount of magnesium that's
why it's greenish blueish if you have a
violet meteor it means it has calcium in
it it has significant amounts of calcium
if you have a reddish meteor it means it
has either significant amounts of oxygen
or nitrogen and if it's a yellowish nice
yellowish meteor it means it has sodium
so depending on the color you can tell
kind of what the chemical composition of
the
object was
right so that's what a meteor is should
you ask for wishes it's your choice you
want to ask for wishes go for it i'm not
sure if it's going to have an effect but
it will make you happy so do it
udid says is it possible to shoot films
in space just like russia is planning to
do i'm not sure what russia is planning
to do but of course you can
shoot friends in space
uh cameras will work in space
and there's plenty of footage of people
in space in this on the space station
uh doing space walks
uh
astronauts bouncing around on the moon
so you can certainly uh film
what's happening in space you can enter
you can if you have the resources you
can even film an entire movie
in space why not
and many of the modern cameras they work
very well in space most of them work
very well in space if you have a gopro
i have a gopro somewhere you have a
gopro it will work well in the vacuum of
space it will work
and i'm sure that asteroid astronauts
must have used gopros during space walks
so yes it is certainly possible to shoot
films in space you can
film entire movies in space
yeah it's possible especially now that
uh space launches are becoming more and
more are becoming cheaper
because of space x what they are doing
they have far surpassed isro in the
um
in the uh
what shall i call it
the amount of money it takes for them to
launch something into space the amount
of money per kilogram of payload is the
lowest when it comes to spacex so yeah
it will be possible
soon maybe
for filmmakers to actually go into space
and shoot things there yeah maybe it
will possibly be possible soon so the
answer to this question is yes
yes
karan says what is the scientific method
of learning well there is something
called the scientific method which is
which is not the scientific method of
learning is the method of doing
scientific research that's a whole
different thing but what is the
scientific method of learning i mean if
i am an individual i want to learn
things
do studies do learning what is a
scientific approach
towards learning something
there are some very simple and basic
concepts the first thing is
don't
believe people's opinions
only trust hard experimental data and
and empirical evidence
yeah
so
in indian philosophy i don't know i
don't remember which school of
philosophy it is it says that there are
multiple kinds of evidence
multiple kinds of evidence exist in the
world yeah
they are called pramanas pramana so the
the best form of evidence the most
superior form of evidence is
pratyakshapraman observational evidence
something you can observe something you
can replicate
that is called a protection
observational evidence
right so that is the best form of
evidence you can rely on that
then there is another form of evidence
called anuman which is inference or
logic so based on what i have observed i
can infer something
or i can use the
i can use logic to make some inferences
that is called anuman anomalist is also
good
but it is not as great or as good as
observational evidence
then you have shabda pramaan which is
people's opinions
look everybody has an opinion everybody
has a nose similarly everybody has an
opinion
even great scientists have opinions that
have turned out to be wrong so opinions
must not be
trusted blindly
yes
if
a very accomplished person a great
scholar has an opinion you should take
it very seriously but always remember
that even the greatest of people can be
wrong in their opinions
so when it comes to evidence
observational evidence empirical
evidence is the most trustworthy the
next most trustworthy
form of evidence is logic and inference
based on observational evidence not
based on opinions and then
opinions are also to be considered but
not given that much weightage so if you
have this clear hierarchy
in your mental makeup you will go well
with your learning right so that is the
scientific approach to learning and you
can apply that to the learning of
history yeah when some
famous people say that this thing
happened but then you find the evidence
that
something else happened then you must
disregard their claims in their opinions
only trust actual evidence hard evidence
archaeological evidence doesn't lie
geological evidence doesn't lie it's
there it's in stone right
written evidence written at the time
something happened that is way more
trustworthy than the opinion of some phd
scholar today and so on so forth so that
is the scientific approach to learning
always emphasize hard evidence you can
only trust hard evidence 100
even then you have to realize that hard
evidence itself can be manufactured or
or or forged
so all you have to be on the lookout for
these things for these things right and
then you have to learn using
well pattern recognition that takes a
lot of time
so but this essentially
in
in brief is the scientific way
of learning anything
misha says dr nishte says what is
current science why is current science
fiction mostly dystopian as opposed to
earlier versions which were so hopeful
and exciting about the future are we
really heading towards a dark and ugly
future see most science fiction comes
from the west
most science fiction that we in india
consume and most of the world consumes
comes out of the west
in the 1950s 1960s the west was very
positive the society was was doing very
well in the us in in western countries
they had won
the great war the second world war the
economy was booming they had all these
nations that they could control
so they had a very good view of the
future so if you see the science fiction
from that time in the 1950s and 60s you
see a very nice optimistic
world view a very optimistic envision
the future space exploration people
going to other planets other worlds
meeting aliens and good stuff overall
the tone was very positive
then
you see
the science fiction becoming darker over
time
and that you see not only in science
fiction you see in other genres also
take batman for instance batman
most of you who watch batman movies
today will feel that batman is a very
dark character very dark and very gloomy
character a mentally disturbed character
with with psychological issues and stuff
like that
there was a batman the original batman
that i watched
was a series that was filmed in the
1960s
which year was that 1966 okay 1966 and
take a look at what that looked like let
me put that on the screen here
does this
version of batman look
dystopian gloomy
it does not
look at the joker
look at batman and robin
this was a very light-hearted original
version of batman
gotham city had criminals but they were
funny criminals and they could be
easily beaten and they were not
as evil as the the the same criminals
the way they're portrayed today look at
them
and if you see the the
you can see various clips of this on
youtube it's really funny very
light-hearted very positive
that is
the the series i watched as a kid i was
not born in 1966 i watched it much later
but
but yeah that's the batman i watched and
if you see batman today
if you just remove the 1966
see today good god how dystopian how
disturbing it is
it's a very dark gloomy
uh look very dark gloomy world
everything is negative there is no
positivity in this so that's what
that's the way batman has evolved over
the decades
and that's the way the science fiction
also has evolved the writing the movies
everything has become darker and darker
uglier and dystopian and
the elements are all negative elements
now so when i say i don't enjoy batman
anymore some people get upset oh it's a
great movie i'm sure it was great for
you but you have not seen what i've seen
my perspective is a much broader
perspective which you may most likely
not have so don't react to what i say
emotionally
somebody asked me about the scientific
method of learning the scientific method
of learning is please put your emotions
aside
if you come up
if you come across new information that
is at odds with what you have learned
thus far don't react emotionally
please stop being emotional indians are
so incredibly emotional why why
please learn something from your
ancestors
stop being so emotional
be a little
more grounded
if you come across new information that
is at odds with what your teachers and
your elders and your society has taught
you
breathe
lumbee
do 60 seconds of pranayama
then look at it again
right
and think about it think analyze it
logically
from the perspective of actual hard
evidence
don't believe people's words and
opinions everybody is and knows
everybody has an opinion
right okay so anyway coming back to this
so that's why
science fiction nowadays is so dark and
all that because
western society is slowly declining
you can see more and more problems every
year in the 1960s even in the 1990s
you would not imagine people pooping on
the streets in the us
today homelessness is rampant people are
actually pooping on the streets san
francisco los angeles those cities can
you believe it in so many other places
overall the society is crumbling
there are so many divisions in society
there is there are
all these hatreds today
so all of that is spilling over into
literature
into movies
into all these different drones
including science fiction
so what's happening is that the western
society is heading towards more darker
times we can see it happening in real
time now
yeah it doesn't mean the whole of
humanity has to follow them
indians love to ape america
stop doing that
please stop doing that
we can build our own future which has
nothing to do with their future
right so be positive be optimistic
watch good movies
movies should make you happy
or they should make you think they
should not leave you with a sense of
gloom and foreboding
you go and watch a movie you walk in
happy you come out with this dark cloud
of your over your head
what's the point
so watch good movies it's fine to watch
movies that have various dark themes but
overall there should be some point to it
not just to to make people unhappy and
all so yeah so my point is we are not
necessarily heading towards a dark and
ugly future not necessarily yeah it's a
so we don't have to follow what they're
doing and ape them
sanat says what's your view on neil
degrasse tyson
as another astrophysicist so i typically
don't express opinions about individuals
because individuals don't matter but in
the rare case of somebody who really
does matter i will talk about them yeah
so
neil degrasse tyson i believe is one of
the most influential and most important
scientists of our time
uh from the perspective
of of influencing so many people right
he has had such a
massive positive influence on society at
large
uh
he has popularized astrophysics and
physics and science overall to an
incredible exchange i don't think
anybody has contributed so much towards
doing that it is not
enough to simply
uh come up with new research one of the
most important thing things a scientist
can do
is to inculcate the love of science in
other people especially youngsters
children teenagers etc you know because
that's where the future scientists will
come from and many of them will have the
aptitude for science but they will not
realize it until you make them fall in
love with science so that's what neil
degrasse tyson has been doing so for for
so many years he's a brilliant speaker
he explains complex things so well so
simply using analogies and all that it's
a lot to learn from him for anybody who
wishes to be a science communicator or
or scientist yeah so i think he's a
brilliant guy very very important in an
influential scientist and
somebody who comes along only once in a
while so yeah i do admire him a great
deal
okay i think we are at the end of
today's questions let me take two three
questions from the chat
can you explain a little bit of astral
projection i don't even know what that
is i don't think it's something to do
with science it's something to do with
spirituality and mysticism so i
apologize i personally know nothing
about it unfortunately
okay what next
james webb space telescope discovers
this detects
carbon dioxide in exoplanet atmosphere
this is not a question this is a
statement and i the statement is correct
it was one of the vast planets i believe
it is a gas giant as far as i remember
and
the telescope has been able to detect
the signature of carbon dioxide in the
atmosphere of this exoplanet so yes it
isn't true but i don't see any question
in there
all right
what's a rogue star how does a star
become a rogue star i think a star can
become a rogue star if it behaves like a
rogue which means it is very naughty
i don't know i'm not sure what a rogue
star is
i'm
not really quite sure what that is
uh
what are maisons
masons are people who who build walls
and buildings masonry
that's what masons are
all right what else
um
is there anything else
i have answered this question multiple
times what is my opinion on vedic rashmi
theory the vedic the so-called vedic
rashmi theory first of all it doesn't
exist in any of the vedas
it is not vedic it is something that
somebody has created in recent times
and there is no science in it
a law a theory of physics needs to have
needs to be based in mathematics it
needs to be able to explain
observational evidence can the vedic
rashmi theory explain
chemistry
can it explain cosmic microwave
background radiation
can does it do that
can it explain the motions of the
planets in the solar system
can it explain various quantum effects
electron
uh tunneling for instance quantum
tunneling
can it explain quantum superposition can
it explain any of these things can it
explain why the moon and the
earth and the moon are
in a resonance state why we only see one
phase of the moon and not the other one
can it explain any of these things
a good theory should be able to firstly
explain everything we know about the
universe thus far
and secondly it should be able to make
predictions
about things we still don't understand
and thirdly it should be falsifiable and
fourthly it should be based in
mathematics
i have tried to look up this thing i
have been able to find no literature on
this anywhere
people point out that some book has been
published i tried to look up the book it
cost 10 000 rupees a good physics theory
a scientific theory should be available
for free for everybody to consume yeah
and and
understand
so i i i'm able to find none of these
things so as far as i'm concerned this
theory is neither vedic it is no neither
is it a scientific theory as far as i
can see i apologize to those whom i have
offended i know we are all very
emotional people if i point put forward
my perspective
people are going to get offended they're
going to react emotionally i bet you or
this object you that
apologies but i stand by my words
all right
okay my dear friends my dear friends
thank you very much for another
wonderful session
and we shall continue this i will see
you in tomorrow's live session which
will be on geopolitics and current
affairs in history
until then
take care
and i will see you soon thank you bye